Okay, so we will start with
with an overview of what we have covered
in this quarter.
So we started the class with just giving
you an overview of LLMs and how over the
past year test time scaling and train
time scaling using self-improvement
techniques where the fundamental loop is
driven by verifiers and feedback from
running those verifiers and getting
rewards and then using reinforcement
learning and even search algorithms to
to help the models to hill climb on math
and coding for example have been a lot
of the focus of initial part of the
class.
From there we started talking about
evolutionary strategies so there was a
whole class on open-endedness where
we're not just um
driving self-improvement loop with um
rewards we also allow the models to just
go explore if the exploration space can
be defined and here we discussed
Alpha Evolve and similar techniques.
Then we moved
to to a paradigm where we build
end-to-end workflows for agents using
tool use and as the models interact with
environments and tools you basically are
able to drive the workflows end-to-end.
And um
if you imagine that you have tasks that
need to be completed over multiple steps
then you do need to have perhaps the
ability to look at knowledge bases so
that requires
retrieval and memory. So basically
as we go towards real-world workflows we
need better planning and multi-step
reasoning in these models so we
discussed
some works around that and how to really
look at evaluations in the next
generation of models and what
capabilities would drive that. And then
we had several guest lectures on post
training and multi model agents and
robotics and reasoning and so on.
Is there anything you would like to add
here?
>> Yeah, I think I think this sounds good.
This was full coverage. I guess so one
of our guest speakers also talked about
um
the symbolic techniques which goes under
the umbrella of tool use and how that
could add to the synthetic data which is
another trend we're seeing.
>> Amazing. Thank you.
So
so I think just to recap and and this uh
the class is named as self-improving
agents. So it's not just focusing on
LLMs, it's focusing on the agent aspect
of it. What I roughly if I were to if if
you were to remind you of what we
discussed in first class um is that what
how is an agent a generalization of LLM?
It has a goal and it will go and
interact with the environment, collect
feedback, and use that feedback to
correct its steps. So they're basically
systems that can direct their own
processes, use tools, and then
accomplish a goal.
And often times in the current paradigm
uh the LLMs uh by themselves are not
powerful enough to drive towards a full
goal. Um they're getting there. So often
times we would handwrite these uh
systems as workflows where you are
orchestrating LLMs and tools. Uh
however, in certain
certain scenarios like coding agents,
you are seeing some of these uh agentic
workflows being driven by themselves. So
it's an exciting time where we are
seeing a lot of progress in this area.
And how we construct these workflows uh
often times means you're orchestrating
LLMs, you're orchestrating verifiers
because you need some form of reward.
You might have LLMs as judges for
verifiers. You might have tool calls.
You might have uh search algorithms in
there. So you might have parallel uh
parallel LLM calls that are going and
doing this kind of search, but overall
since uh agentic workflow is driving
towards a goal, it needs the capability
to plan and to
reason over multiple steps, correct
itself if it were going in the wrong
direction, and overall keep improving in
its capabilities, which is where the
self-improvement aspect comes in. So, in
this lecture as we wanted we wanted to
cover some future research areas. So,
we organized it as key ideas from
certain papers that both cover the
self-improvement side of things and just
generally the
efficiency side of things for
intelligence, both of which we believe
are extremely important directions in
the next research areas.
So,
for the first three papers that I will
cover um
I'll just present the key ideas, but let
me just present what
why those papers were chosen and what
are the key ideas that they kind of um
point in terms of next steps and
directions. So, what we learned in the
classes a lot about say test time
scaling where you could
improve
by having multiple samples and majority
voting and so on. And then train time
scaling where you can use that feedback
in the inference loop to and get rewards
to drive that self-improvement loop.
Often times this is still limited to
narrow domains like math and coding. So,
how do you get generalization across
these domains?
And how do you generally get those
reasoning chains
to be diverse enough so that you can
continue to drive that self-improvement
loop is something that is
an important research area even now.
An important aspect of
building these self-improvement loops
continues to be verification. So, how do
you have robust verification techniques
or meta verification techniques where
you verify
what was going into the reasoning chain
is
often quite valuable. So that's another
area that the second paper I will
present the ideas on will cover. And the
third aspect is that
even though we talk about train time
scaling that
the prompts that go into training these
models
get selected very statically and require
humans to select them.
So
how do you break through the data
barriers so that the self-improvement
loop can pick the right set of data that
drives that loop.
So that's going to be the first part of
the focus and the second part of the
focus will be focused on just what
drives
efficiency for intelligence. So
intelligence per what aspects?
So let's take a quick look at some of
the ideas that might drive the
self-improvement loop further in the
next generation of systems and given how
fast the field is moving
maybe we'll be teaching papers on each
of this next time.
So the first paper that we cover is
coming from multi-agent fine-tuning
which focuses on self-improvement with
diverse reasoning chains.
The key idea of this paper is that
pre-training computer and instruction
tuning is bottlenecked by
so pre-training computers are
compression of internet scale data and
instruction fine-tuning often requires
real human data where you
need human preferences to decide what is
good model response and bad response
bad model response. So an alternative to
this is that you can use the data
generated by LLMs which is often called
a synthetic data and you can do
iterative fine-tuning where you
generate possible solutions and filter
out the incorrect ones. This is called
rejection sampling and fine-tune only on
the good ones. Now there are many
variants star and so on which uh can
help drive this loop even better. We
covered star in in class. Uh you can
even add reasoning chains in in in that
process.
But, what typically happens is that if
you're using a single uh large language
model to generate the data, then uh
it will generate solutions that will be
very similar, and often time the
performance increase will start uh will
stop uh after a few uh iterations or
after tens of iterations. And typically
this problem is uh
uh comes down to really the notion of
lack of diversity. So, when uh you look
at model training at the pre-training
scale, the data is so diverse because it
was generated over such a long time uh
by humans, so it
it is quite diverse, and that helps to
uh helps improve the performance. But,
when a single large language model is
generating outputs for a set of prompts,
it will not have very diverse responses
even at high temperatures. And if uh so,
the intuitive solution for this often
means that you can use multiple agents
uh which are specialized in some way,
and then
>> [snorts]
>> use them to uh
improve the diversity. So, what this
paper proposes, for example, is multiple
specialized agents uh for generations
that will then produce uh diverse
initial solutions. So, they they train
generation agents and critic agents. So,
um the generation agents will help
generate a lot of diverse initial
solutions, while the critic agents will
evaluate and refine the solutions. Uh
so, those are specialists as well. So,
if you were to look at um step-by-step
process, and we don't need to go through
every single uh detail in the algorithm
below, uh but uh the generation agent
will come up with an initial answer, um
and then there will be debate over
multiple rounds. So, uh what the
generation agent will In the In the
initial step, it will just have the
initial answer, but in the subsequent
steps, it will summarize uh and get a
summary of all other agents' responses,
and use that also as part of generating
the next response.
The goal of the critic critic agent is
to critique this updated set of answers.
So, basically, if you're doing any
iterations, there's an initial response
from each of the generation agents, then
you do a summary across all of these
agents, and then the critic agent will
critique this updated set of answers.
So, it's very similar to what you guys
were already familiar with. The main
difference here is that instead of
getting um
uh the critique over a single agent's
response, you're actually using multiple
agents' responses, and then then
specializing
uh and summarizing across them. What
this enables is that uh you have some
form of diversity even at the generation
stage before you're critiquing the
answers. So, you basically get majority
voting for free just by having multiple
agents, and
uh
assuming that these are trained slightly
differently, you
uh you get diversity for free.
So, uh the generation models in this
particular case are fine-tuned from the
same base models. So, they uh and and
the goal there is to produce good
answers given a question. So,
uh over multiple iterations, what
they're doing is they're taking outputs
and filtering for a match with the
majority vote, and then they're doing a
SFT on this list of prompt and response
pairs. Um if you were looking at a very
naive version of doing this, uh you
could just use different models, which
is something that
uh people do in practice as well. So,
they will get very different responses
with different prompts. So, that's the
poor man's version of doing uh multiple
generations.
And uh the critic models in this
particular paper was proposed as uh
The critic models will basically take
the
uh
input uh the updated answer, and then
select the best one. So, they are also
fine-tuned.
Uh and uh these are um
fine tuned on a mix of trajectories
where answers correct at the start and
then it's corrected over a course of
debate. So basically the critic model is
learning how to uh contrast the um
correct and the incorrect answer.
So to summarize the whole process, um
there is end generation models and
they're all each producing an output.
The summarization happens. So you can
imagine that either you summarize it
with a model or you can just concatenate
the responses of all the
uh models. Then there is a
um critic critique process on that and
that's uh added to the um input uh and
then then you do a second round where
all of the models generates
outputs, updated answers, and then then
you do uh majority voting on top of that
and again summarize the responses and
you can continue this process in form of
a debate in some ways. So uh those
trajectories can then be used to fine
tune different um different uh critiques
as well.
So how does this help? Um why did we
discuss this? So I think the key metric
that we're looking for is that
uh
on the x-axis you're looking at uh how
many iterations of fine tuning it has
gone through and on the y-axis you
either have the negative log likelihood
or you have the embedding uh
dissimilarity. Uh the negative log
likelihood is just uh a proxy for
performance and the embedding
dissimilarity the
higher the
higher uh the value, uh the more um
diverse it is. So what we see on the
left is for two open source models uh
when they go and do fine tuning, they're
actually able to continue to increase
performance when they do this
multi-agent fine tuning. So um and Llama
3 seems more responsive to this
technique. Um I think the right side is
more interesting as to
uh
as they're going through this process,
uh the responses continue to stay quite
diverse. And this is over math as a
dataset.
And overall, they tried this
again in math over three open-source
models. Uh and since they were going
with fine-tuning, they had to stick with
open-source models, but with multi-agent
techniques, they were able to continue
to see improvements even over multiple
steps of fine-tuning. While for
single-agent fine-tuning,
the accuracy collapses or doesn't
continue to improve.
And uh they also show that
not just in domain, which is math, in
adjacent domains like GSM8K, this is a
slightly older piece of work, so
the numbers are not that high, but in
even in adjacent domains like GSM8K, the
model the fine-tuned agents actually
show higher performance.
Uh so this technique actually does help
even it
So it generalizes beyond just the
in-domain uh datasets that it's trained
on.
So that's first set of comments. Um
So what that roughly says is that if we
want self-improvement, the reasoning
chains that are provided to the model to
drive those need to be diverse in some
way, and how you do generate that, one
technique could be based on having
multiple models or multiple agents
generate those kind of chains.
A second problem that's very challenging
and we covered actually in
the first few lectures is around
verification. So it's quite hard to
verify
model outputs.
And typically, you would just look at
the
outcome. So if you have a math problem
or a theorem proving uh
a theorem proof, what you will look at
is the final outcome, and then you have
an outcome reward model. So does that
match the ground truth? And then you
will say that this verifies. One of the
questions that we discussed
in the
verification lecture is that what
happens if the reasoning chains are
wrong and will that lead the model
astray and or or will that
cause uh some performance gap uh at the
end. And
we also realized that process reward
models are quite hard to build. So,
DeepSeek-Math V2 is a recent paper that
came out which tries to show that at
least in the theorem proving domain, it
is possible to build uh
self-verification loops uh which are
automated. So, uh that's a very
interesting uh concept.
Um
just to remind you on what I was saying,
the current reinforcement learning
approach assumes that final answer will
match the ground truth and that's how uh
you're basically creating the rewards.
So, this has enabled saturation of
multiple benchmarks like AMIE or uh
other math-related benchmarks, but often
times uh even when you have the correct
answer, you might not have the correct
reasoning. And if you are actually
trying to get the models to do better in
theorem proving, you do require rigorous
step-by-step derivation which um the
final output doesn't quite give you.
Now, the interesting aspect is that uh
the large language models are often
trained on quantitative reasoning. So,
the proofs that they might generate are
mathematically invalid. And
uh if you ask them to uh verify, they
will claim that the incorrect proofs are
valid. So, LLM as a judge technique
doesn't quite work uh here. But, if you
actually have expert humans look look at
these proofs, um
they will be able to look at the proof
and and kind of uh reason about the fact
that they know this area, they can
reason about the fact and say that,
"Okay, this proof has issues. It's just
um not making sense because uh this next
step is not following from the last step
or there's reasoning gaps in the
reference in the proof uh solution."
So, uh what uh DeepSeek-Math V2 proposes
is that instead of uh just training uh
the reward models, they train uh
verifiers, so meta verifiers basically.
So, they get humans to identify issues
in the proofs
without any reference solutions, and
based on that they train LLMs to
identify issues in the proof and
improve upon those. And then if you will
find that there So, you basically have
trained a model which can now critique
the proofs themselves.
So,
what the final architecture for
DeepSeek-Math V2 looks like. You folks
are already familiar with the fact that
there's a generator and a verifier
typically in the in the loop for
building
chain time scaling systems. So, you are
you have one model that is producing
proofs and another model that is uh
perhaps verifying things. So, it's
identifying issues. What DeepSeek-Math
V2 adds is this notion of meta verifier.
So, you have
a meta verifier that will review the
verifier's analysis for whether it makes
sense or whether there are issues with
the proofs. And then the verifier is
trained to
take these issues and then score the
proofs on a scale of 0.5 and 1.
So, the verifier will then go improve
the generator and the generator will
produce harder proofs which will then go
improve the verifier. So, there's this
basically this ends up being a loop in
some way.
And the other interesting aspect here is
that because
once you seed the data for
finding incorrect proofs, then you can
actually automate that kind of labeling.
So, you don't have to just rely on
humans identifying issues in the proofs
once the model once the meta verifier
starts to learn this.
So,
this notion of meta verification is
generally quite interesting in that
verifiers can get correct score
when the reasoning chains are incorrect.
For example,
they might come up with fabricated
errors. So, meta verification has
evaluation of this analysis to these
issues that the
that the verifier a verifier here is LLM
as a judge uh
do these identified issues actually
exist? Does the score follow from the
issues? So, they're basically analyzing
whether the verifier did a good job or
not. And then they have experts annotate
the quality of this evaluation. And just
by adding this additional block, they
are able to improve the quality. So,
it's almost like you had reasoning
chains and then now you have um the
verifier
over those reasoning chains, which is
basically saying that is this evaluation
correct or not? Um so,
it there is an LLM as a judge, which is
identifying the issues in this reasoning
chain and then
do those issues exist or not is what
meta verification is uh looking for.
If you look at the results here,
um
just with this iterative optimization,
uh I think all of those are familiar
that a lot of the RL loop uh
often uh is built on top of GRPO. Um in
this particular case, they're building
on top of DeepSeek V3 base models. So,
just the verification generation loop
now um benchmarked on IMO problems and
CNML problems. Um this was present like
the Gemini version of that was presented
by
uh one of our guest lecturers, but this
is an open-source version that was
released uh recently.
Uh they are able to show that in
eight iterations, um just with positive
one, the proof score continues to climb
just with that iterative loop. And then
if you have best at 32, best at 32 means
you pick the best solution out of 32
generated proofs. Um there you are
almost getting to 42% in uh proof score
uh for IMO short list of 2024. So, this
is quite promising as a hill climbing
technique, which can suggests that there
is some promise if you can identify the
issues in the reasoning chains and
actually push the model or nudge the
model towards correcting them.
So, overall um
the insights here are that
the best proofs will achieve higher
verification scores and the generator
can learn to differentiate higher
quality proofs from flawed proofs and
the self-verification as a result can uh
basically uh have this better
improvement loop. So, verification can
be a bottleneck and this is one way to
break that bottleneck.
Overall, I think if you were to try to
generalize this technique in other
areas, what you're basically looking for
is you're if you have LLM-based
verifiers, you need need to find a way
to get them to identify issues without
reference solutions. That's what this
paper is relying on. Then you need some
form of an additional block which is
meta meta verification so that it can
reduce the chance of hallucinated issues
that were identified by the verifier.
And
then you add an additional incentive for
the generator to maximize
quality through deliberate reasoning.
So, you're basically improving the
quality of the model responses here.
So, overall, this notion of
self-verification is introduced by our
Deep Seek Deep Seek Math V2 and it
starts to
break the bottleneck in in verification
if you can
make that more automated end-to-end.
Uh of course, this is still limited by
uh by domains where verification is
easier
uh rather than more difficult.
Okay.
So, we covered through um
what is the diversity in reasoning
chains and we discussed a bit about um
the verification bottleneck in the
models where oftentimes um
to get the models to
uh, get over the bottleneck of, uh,
verification, you need some form of meta
verification techniques and N Deep Seek
Math V2, uh, publishes that in open
source. A third problem that you have to
solve is this notion of, um,
what data or what prompts, uh, should I
train on? Um, so there's this very
interesting paper that has not, um,
uh, seen, uh, much, uh, um,
use yet, but is quite promising and
interesting is that, um,
you basically, uh, have the models
propose the set of tasks that they
should go train on that are just, um, at
the edge of, uh, what they have learned.
So,
to remind you, typically in the current
AI training stack, um, you are either
using human curated re- reasoning
traces, so that's for the supervised
learning stage, or for reinforcement
learning with verifiable rewards, you
are expecting some experts to curate the
question-answer pairs, but that that
basically requires that if you're
constructing such, uh, model in, um,
math, then you need math experts. If
it's an IMO problems, then you need IMO
experts, or if it is in coding, then you
need, um, strong software coders. Uh,
so,
as, uh, the models continue to surpass
human intelligence, um, the
the ability to find more and more
experts and more and more such tasks
starts to be, uh, limiting.
So, what this, uh, paper proposes, um,
and this idea is still very new, is that
a single model can both propose tasks
and then solve them, so it
it's almost goes to the other extreme of
like, we should not really need an
external, um,
external source of data. So, basically,
we don't should not need human
generated, um,
uh, prompts uh, to help climb on. The
model itself will propose the tasks and
then then it will go solve them and uh,
so that's a very interesting set of
ideas
and uh
it is feasible in certain domains. So
they focus more on coding as a domain
and they
effectively construct three types of
tasks
abduction deduction and induction and I
will explain this diagram in the
subsequent slides but effectively what
this is saying is that in the proposal
stage
they will
construct the tasks based on this task
types and then come up with a reward to
select which tasks make sense and in the
solution stage they will verify
and then have an accuracy reward and
then that can help give a joint update
on the model itself as opposed to
just one sided updates.
So
what is the proposer? How is the
proposer proposing tasks? That's quite
interesting. So it's effectively based
on code coding paradigm so it's
effectively saying that
you have deduction tasks where
you are generating program and input um
and the
environment is executing to get get
output. So this is your usual
um
come up with a program and an input pair
and then the environment will execute to
get outputs.
Abduction tasks they're similar to
deduction you're generating the program
and inputs and
environment again computes outputs but
induction tasks are different. It
samples an existing program and then
generates a new inputs for it
plus a natural language message
describing the function and the
environment then goes and executes and
and kind of decides whether this um
this is going in the right direction or
not.
So
what I and another interesting bit that
I should mention here is that the
proposer will be conditioned on past
here. So
I'll cover that in a later slide because
otherwise it will get confusing, but it
will be basically conditioned on past
generated examples that are explicitly
prompted
so that they're basically added to
promote diversity.
So how do you how do you select tasks?
The proposal will get a reward based on
optimizing for task difficulty. So if
when the solver so
each of the tasks that are generated are
passed to the solver
and success rate is um
zero, then you get a zero reward and if
the
success rate is non-zero, then you
basically get one minus average success
rate and the kind of tasks that you want
to select are
the [snorts] ones that are not trivial
and the ones that are not impossible, so
there is some ability to continue to
learn. So you end up selecting tasks
that are of moderate difficulty where
solver will sometimes succeed and
sometimes fail and this will generally
help with uh
getting the model to learn. So that's
the goal of the
proposer is to
generate tasks for optimal task
difficulty at a current set of model
weights and as the model becomes more
capable, then the proposal should learn
to propose harder problems.
Um of course, if you generate tasks,
then you need to somehow make sure that
these are valid tasks. So in the coding
abstraction, one can run program
integrity, so you can actually execute
these tasks and see whether there are
any errors. You can do safety checks.
You can also make sure that if you run
these inputs multiple times, you get
exactly same outputs because in code
that's possible. So
the proposed tasks before it goes into
the training pipeline is validated. So
that's one way to make sure that
um
the proposal doesn't just um hack and
come up with garbage tasks.
And in terms of
there's a buffer that is kept. So,
for
every seat triplet like there's an
identifying like basically the the
input, output, and the program for each
of those triplet tasks, you're adding
them to the task buffer and the proposer
can sample references from the our
buffer. So,
there's some sort of a buffer that is
kept
along with how
how many times the model is succeeding
or failing on this. So, this is
basically leading to this idea of
curriculum learning that is evolving
over time.
And
why is this exciting or interesting? I
mean, on coding benchmarks, this notion
starts to let you hill climb despite
having much human curated data,
which you know, human humans can
generate a lot of coding data, but that
after a while synthetic data or some
This is almost a play on synthetic data
in some ways, but it's um
generating that in the loop at the task
level as as well. So, what they show is
that they're able to get state of the
art on coding benchmarks even though
they didn't have any human curated data
on the prompt side, and they are able to
outperform models trained on tens of
thousands of expert examples. Some
emerging behaviors that they show are
that the complexity metrics increase
over time. So, that can be expected if
the proposer is continuing to increase
the difficulty of what it's learning.
And another aspect is that the diversity
of programs and answers when the loop is
set up correctly is is improving and the
proposer is actually increasingly
generating more and more difficult tasks
as it's
as the training is progressing. So, in
in some ways it's almost like game
theory where the proposer and solver are
slightly adversarial, but overall
they're helping each other improve in
some ways.
So, this is solving through the
bottleneck of which tasks to go uh train
the models on.
So, if you were to uh look at takeaways
here, I think it's it's basically going
down the path of like the the task
selection problem on which these models
um run their self-improvement loop
should not get bottlenecked on human
data because otherwise you are very
bottlenecked on which human experts as
long as you can have some form of
verification there.
And uh you need some form of uh ability
to do curriculum learning. So,
uh this particular technique definitely
relies on that. And uh even though they
only
hill climb on self-proposed code tasks,
they actually see strong performance on
both coding and math math benchmarks.
So, that's actually surprising that they
are also seeing strong performance on
math benchmarks, but one can explain
that from other results that have been
seen in the field. And overall, larger
models get bigger gains relative to
smaller models. So,
uh this is another uh idea in the space
of uh improving the self-improvement
loop that uh seems quite promising and
uh continuing to hill climb in that
area.
>> Uh can I add something on on the
previous? So, I feel like we are seeing
the same thing. Like, we learned about
Swirl, the step-by-step RL with
synthetic data. Like, I feel like the
findings here and there really kind of
resonate with each other in the sense
that uh synthetic data, like model
generating its own training data, can
improve the model not only on the
the task that the generation is
happening on, but also in
transferability. Like, in Swirl, it was
on us to a multi-hop question answering
with retrieval, but then as more
synthetic data was generated and RL
training was done, the model was getting
better at other tool calling, like
calling a Python and solving math
problems and vice versa. So, it seems
like there is this like clear kind of
repeated trend that we are seeing in
terms of synthetic data generation by
the model and generalization. And the
other piece that's interesting again
that
kind of is the same kind of observation
is that larger models seems to be better
at absorbing this kind of data flywheel
and also generalizing through that.
Uh especially when it comes to in swirl
at least on the RL optimization side,
which is like an interesting
observation.
>> Great. Great.
Uh where where would you take it from
here
from what you learn in swirl, right? So,
I was going to summarize then you can
add more bullet points. I I think to me
uh
to achieve true generalization and
reasoning, we really need that notion of
diversity um
in the reasoning chain. So, that that
was the first set of comments I was
making and how we achieve that um
continues to be an open problem. Uh we
need better verification and the more we
can break that verifier loop in a way
where uh we are not bottlenecked by
humans or or tasks that are uh
verified only through human experts, uh
the better off we are in some ways.
Like, building reward models is
challenging.
And then I think the third is the
selection of data itself. Um
there's only so much uh
data that can be curated by humans for
what prompts go in. Uh so, that breaking
that barrier is also quite important in
next generation of
uh self-improving models. What else do
you would add there?
>> Yeah, I think uh
one just uh based on these kind of
existing work
uh
something that would be interesting is
that how much we can push the front here
of the self-improvement just
only be based on the verifiable domains
that we can generate synthetic data and
bring it back to the model
on diverse task on diverse verifiable
task, how much that pushes the
performance and generalizes to other
domains where we don't have uh
automated verification. Like, can we
generally make the model smarter and
smarter in areas that we can verify
verify
and
uh minimize or
remove the need for label data in on
non-verifiable
domains based on that. So, I think that
would be an interesting kind of research
area, of course, a very compute-heavy
research experiment.
>> Uh there are there are some questions
that people are asking. Uh what are some
other applications of AI that don't fall
into verifiable problems?
>> So, it
So, it comes in I I can just think about
uh
some uh areas that verification is very
slow.
Uh like, scientific discovery, running a
very slow simulation in chip design that
takes like a few days to run it to run
to collect one kind of reward signal, or
running this chemical experiment that
you actually need to like go to a wet
lab and run things and see like what the
output, the quality, or the reward is.
Those are the domains that the
verification is really hard because
in RL fine-tuning, we need or in test
time scaling, we need these verifiers to
be almost instant, right? Or we can wait
a little bit. Maybe we can wait minutes.
Maybe we can allow like 1 hour, but if
this in this RL training route we RL
training, we need like hundreds or
thousands of steps of iteration,
we can't wait like days
uh or like someone a human in the loop
to collect the reward for us.
So those are the non verifiable domains.
Those are some examples of non non
verifiable domains.
>> I think truly non verifiable also comes
from creativity or any metrics that
where where there's subjectivity in some
ways.
>> Like creative writing, right? It's like
a
designing an exact reward function for
that is hard.
But of course we can always model that,
but then you you can the RL or the agent
can do reward hacking if the model is
slightly off
off base, yeah.
>> Any other questions from the class on
those aspects?
>> Yeah, we have one question. Can you hear
us?
>> Yes, we can hear you.
>> Uh
you mentioned
the harder areas to verify. Like how are
people attempting to
uh solve that?
Like for example, like chip design or
like
like bio
discoveries.
>> Um so one way to to go about it is to
train a model like a separate reward
model that can predict the outcome of a
simulation. So instead of actually
running those expensive uh simulations
or emulations or true experiment, you
collect a lot of data on them offline
and then you train a reward model that
for a given input it can predict the
quality of the output and you use this
reward model as your verification
object like uh
in the loop of RL optimization and so
on. But of course the generality of the
reward model is a function of how much
data you have and
um
it can
uh can be inaccurate and that can cause
problems.
So that's that's one area. Akanksha, do
you have any?
>> So
I think we talked about chip design and
so on, right? But even even before going
to chip design, just the kernel bench
stuff that was done at Stanford in your
lab.
Even there, for example, um
get get you get compiler execution, so
you can see that did you generate the
right code or not? You can get some
metrics, but
there's a class project that is actually
trying to read performance profiles as
you make things more complex and that's
a harder problem. So you basically
even though you might be able to do
design optimized kernels for simple
enough things, but if you actually
concatenate all of these things together
and you want to
performance profile and and change parts
of the code that are
not optimized, that's a harder problem
in general in some ways and often times
the way people will go about solving it
is okay, the models can
solve maybe kernel optimization problem,
so maybe I break down the problem into
sub parts and then then get the model to
look at each part and then have some
reference solutions to look at a
knowledge base. I'm literally describing
a class project right now. So what I'm
trying to say here is that it's
because of this being a hard enough
problem and the models not being at that
capability, often it requires breaking
down the problem in interesting ways to
what what the models are able to do now.
Okay.
Let's move to
more along the lines of okay, we can do
the self-improvement, but you're now
doing a lot more inference and there's a
cost to this intelligence. So Azalia
will cover more on how to get efficiency
there.
>> Sounds good. Should I I, uh, present
myself or would you like scroll? Like
how what would
>> Uh, whatever is fastest. I can continue
to if you just tell me next I'll
continue to this.
>> Okay. Okay. Sounds good. So, next,
please.
Um, so this is a recent work, uh, that
we did, uh, in collaboration with uh,
Professor Ray and uh, Professor John
Hennessy and a large team of uh,
great collaborators. Um, so in this
project we're what we're looking for is
like looking into the the trends that
are happening on the model side and also
on the hardware accelerator side and
we're what we are interested in, uh, in
kind of like
uh, thinking about the future and
thinking about how the workloads and AI
inference,
uh,
uh, is going to look like in terms of
like the type of the size of the models
and the type of accelerators that we're
going to need to serve them. Uh, next,
please.
So, uh,
right now we call we are in the
mainframe uh, era meaning that uh,
the
LLMs that we're running using ChatGPT,
Gemini, uh, a lot of these uh, larger
models that we're running, all of them
are being run on cloud, uh,
we don't we don't run them locally
because these models are large. Uh, some
of them we even don't have access to
them, they're proprietary and the even
the open source one for the larger
models we're still using cloud to run
these models.
Uh, and at the same time what the
observation is that the demand for
compute
as a result is exploding like Google
Cloud uh, had grew in something in the
order of 1200x in the last 12 20 months
in terms of the compute serving in video
had a 10x year over year kind of growth
growth. And this is like crazy, right?
These numbers are
explicitly driven by AI and as a result
you're going to need something in the
order of 250 gigabyte gigawatt of data
centers
to be able to serve this demand right
now and again this is exploding. So that
means you're going to need more and more
energy kind of supply for these data
centers.
On the right side we are this we are
showing this graph of the number of
tokens
that are kind of like
from from on the Google side has been
processed. So in the February of last
year it was 160 trillion and in October
of this year it was 1.3
quadrillion.
So this is like one of the fastest
growing compute demands that we are
seeing in history.
Next please.
>> [clears throat]
>> At the same time so we looked into like
what kind of workloads are or the type
of activities or AI serving
demand that we are observing and there
from this
data set this very large scale data set
of chat GPT users it turns out that
something in the order of 77%
of requests are for task like practical
guidance, information,
like asking for information or writing
and a lot of these task
it turns out that we don't need the very
best frontier models to ask to to answer
them correctly. Rather small smaller and
local models can be used to address to
address them. So on the right side you
are seeing this kind of like categories
of user queries, the type of user
queries that exist and over time and
what is interesting here is that of
course users are going to ask more and
more complex problems from the chatbots
over time because the chatbots are
getting better, but still it's kind of
like the vast majority of the type of
queries that are being asked are on the
on the side of again the simpler side of
complexity that can be addressed by
smaller models rather than
large proprietary models.
Next, please.
Um
another trend that is happening right
now is the improvements in local
inference accelerators. So, the graph on
the right what it shows is us since 2012
up until now uh
we we saw something like 126x
improvement in the GPU memory of the
local accelerators and right now
we have laptops that our MacBooks could
have
something in the order of 100 GB of
memory and that means that we can fit
very very large model
if we
especially if you serve the model in
quantized versions like in eight and so
the larger some of the largest models
that are out there we can take them and
serve them locally. This is like a very
interesting trend that is following this
other trend that
a lot of user queries are addressable by
smaller models.
Next, please.
So, the question that we wanted to
answer here is that
uh
what role can local inference play in
re-redistributing
the inference demand? So, we have all
this traffic right now that pretty much
all of it is going to cloud.
Pretty much all of it is going is going
to these accelerators like H100s and
TPUs and GP200s, GP300s. But,
the trends right now are suggesting that
maybe we can do something different
here. And so, let's see the next slide.
Uh so, in order to look into this more
systematically, we first did did
uh
define this new metric that looks into
not only the capability or the way the
models are the accuracy of the models,
but also on the efficiency side. So, on
the capability side, we are looking in
this metric that I'm about to define
called intelligence per watt is looking
into the percentage of
uh of the queries that are being uh are
that are addressable by the model in in
for the single turn and reasoning uh
type of queries. And when I say local
models right now, at least in this
study, we considered those are the
models that are 20 have 20 billion
active parameters or less.
Um and on the efficiency side is how
much uh
useful compute we can get from these uh
per watt from running these models on
our local hardware. So, in short, the
definition of intelligence per watt is
the average task accuracy divided by the
average power draw to uh
to to solve this task by the model.
Uh next, please.
And we looked into a variety of uh
models, hardware, work uh type of tasks,
and uh evaluation metrics.
Uh we looked into more than 20 local
models and like quant, GPTQ, llama 3,
and so on.
Uh we looked into both enterprise
accelerators and local accelerators.
Uh
the type of workloads we looked into, as
you can see here, were there were 1
million queries from sourced from chat
GPT
and other reasoning
benchmarks such as natural reasoning,
MMLU Pro, and Super GPQA.
Um and we also looked into the
evaluation metrics such as accuracy,
energy, latency,
uh the compute used, and so on. And all
of this data, so this massive data we
used it to up to understand the trends,
but we are also
uh open-sourcing all of these kind of
different metrics across different
uh
uh type of on the underlying model and
hardware substrates.
Next, please.
So, here is our find our findings.
Uh it turns out that local models are
not only are very very good already, but
the trend of their improvement is also
very interesting. So, since 2023,
um there was a 3.1x
improvement in the accuracy or the
portion of the chat queries that they
could add they could solve.
Um this is very very fast, and this
happened in only 2 years. Um and right
now they could among the queries that I
described in the previous slide, they
could address something in the order of
88.7%
of all these queries. Uh this is a very
very large number number.
Um another observation, which is like
kind of not very surprising, is that
local accelerators, in terms of their
efficiency, they lag behind enterprise
chips.
Uh for example, an Apple M4 Max, uh,
it delivers 1 and 1/2,
uh,
X lower intelligence per watt than a
B200. And the reason for that is that
these B200s are extremely, like,
optimized to run language model
workloads, whereas an Apple M4, of
course, is optimized to run these AI
metrics, but there are other metrics,
other other kind of workloads that are
out there that, uh, they're optimized
for. And in general, while designing
these chips, the understanding wasn't
that
the LLMs are going to be running
locally.
That's why, like, the majority of focus
of chip designers are on this cloud
cloud scale uh, chips for running these
workloads.
And lastly,
there is this other very important
observation that the intelligence
efficiency, like, or the improvement in
this IQ EW metric, is something in the
order of 5.3X over the last 2 years. So,
3.1X of it is coming from better models,
and another 1.7X of it is coming from
the improvement in the hardware, and the
how the hardware is becoming more and
more efficient. So, both of these, uh,
so the the all of these, uh,
both of these trends, one is that local
models are, like, becoming better and
better. They can
solve problems, uh, that they couldn't
solve before at this, like, very
accelerated rate. At the same time,
uh, model efficiency is becoming better,
and hardware efficiency is becoming
better. This suggests that we're heading
towards this future that more and more
of this traffic can be addressed or can
be solved by models that we can run on
our edge device, for example, on our
laptop or on our, uh, phone device in
the future.
Uh next, please.
Um so, uh
let's just go to the next slide. Uh
so,
with that, uh
I get back to the IPW and the future
directions for that in a second, but
given this observation and everything
else that we have kind of learned in
this class,
there are a few directions that are
remain like open. There are a lot of
interesting research questions around it
that can be that are not addressed yet,
and it's going to be interesting to work
on.
Uh one is the the fund foundational
principles in test time scaling,
um and learning from this like
new kind of era of synthetic data and
synthetic data flywheel that these
models are creating.
Uh right now, the way we are approaching
it is through RL, through collecting
this data, and then fine-tuning the
models.
Uh but, it kind of like suggests that
there is more here, like our
understanding of
um
First of all, why is why are we seeing
this kind of property? Like, what does
it suggest from the model that as they
ask the model a question over and over
again through test time scaling, what is
happening that these correct answers are
coming out? Like, what are the best
practices to kind of distill these
successful trajectories back to the
model.
Um these are still open questions, and
there is a very clear segway from this
synthetic data flywheel
uh kind of phenomenon back to continual
learning.
Um
something that is that seems like maybe
it's not really we haven't gotten it
right yet is the following. Like, us
humans, like as we solve tasks, as we
uh solve problems and study and do new
things, there is this continual kind of
progress in how our brain develops and
how we become more and more skillful.
Whereas for the models, it seems like
mostly there's this offline process of
like
here is like some agent take up uh kind
of experiences that are generated and
then maybe after some time there's like
this fine-tuning process of
of the model.
Uh it is not something that happens on
the go.
Uh and there is this kind of a mismatch
between
human behavior and model behavior that's
a concept like continual learning could
potentially answer. Like, what are the
new practices that we can bring in model
development that we can kind of like
bring these
uh positive experiences and learning
from negative experiences and type of
problem-solving that the model do back
into the model in a more natural way
uh that is different from the current
like
asynchronous like data generation and on
and fine-tuning paradigm.
Um
Uh the last piece is the infra for the
high-throughput low latency test time
scaling. So, again, a a very
um
the way we do test time scaling, whether
it's repeated sampling, whether it's uh
these kind of like back and forth in
terms of uh
up updates that we do to the previous
generations, we do tool calling, we do
this and that. That is very different
from the
current mainstream chatbot usage, which
is uh just like kind of mostly
single-turn back and forth with the
model.
And that what that means is that there
are very a lot of opportunities for
doing systems and inference optimization
work
uh for these type of test time scaling.
Uh my lab did some of this work like
works like hydrogen, Tokamak
uh and these things are going to matter
again a lot more in the future because
uh these methods are becoming more and
more mainstream. So, that means we need
to have uh specific ways to deal or
optimize the systems and the underlying
compute for them. So, overall, it seems
like pre-training
uh looking at the the figure on the
bottom of the slide, pre-training a lot
of interesting work in there. This
course or our series of lectures touched
less on that even though uh Akanksha is
an expert on pre-training, but we mostly
focused on post-training and the test
time scaling methods. And there is this
new kind of on unleashed area of like
synthetic data flywheel and continual
learning that is happening in this kind
of connection between the fine-tuning
and online learning and test time
scaling that we hope that all of you
learned a ton about it, but there's also
a lot of interesting unsolved challenges
that you can address going forward. Uh
next slide, please.
Um
uh going back to the IPW metric and the
observation about the shift the possible
shift from everything on cloud to a lot
more locally
uh
also suggests new direction in terms of
inference
uh serving engines that are hybrid
uh that we we can kind of smoothly route
traffic between our local and cloud kind
of uh models and accelerators depending
on the need and the complexity of
uh of the resources.
Um
The other direction here again is new
model architectures and kernels that we
can use for any energy-efficient
inference, especially on the local
accelerators that we have, which is like
a which is like a
area that has much less
uh kind of focus on compared to the
cloud cloud accelerators.
Um and the other important piece is that
energy is going to be the most like kind
of uh valuable resource that we have
going forward. Uh and
uh metrics such as intelligence per watt
and better ways of our understanding of
measuring energy and watt and power
usage and optimizing for that again is
going to be very very important. And
that is an area that
uh
is less focused on right now in terms of
like the metric of the target metric of
optimization, but we expect that it's um
it becomes more mainstream and more
popular
uh going forward.
And
I think that's the last slide on the
future directions.
Um Akanksha, you're muted.
Okay, there's some some things in chat.
So,
um
I'll start with the first question here.
Do you think this is more pertaining
This is more pertaining to memory
systems
or the LLMs themselves?
I'm guessing uh So, whoever asked this
question, can you ask it real time
perhaps to uh put a little bit more
context there? Otherwise, we're guessing
the question.
>> Yeah, happy to.
Uh
yeah, I was just referring to a few
slides back when you were talking about
that continual learning like from
failures and success. Um
Do you think that we're going to see
more of that in
you know, long-term memory systems and
architectures or the you know, what's
designed around an LLM or the models
themselves?
In terms of what's improved and what's
worked on.
>> So, I think the continual learning idea
that might pertain to long-term memory
systems with that's that would be the
human analog of it, but if you're trying
to but but before we even go there,
get even in multi-step reasoning
learning from success or failures or
getting the model to keep that skill set
and update things in the weights the or
in subset of weights in a useful way
like can you learn a new skill? Can you
learn how to learn is is an important
capability that we basically don't have
right now.
Like if you can watch videos robots try
this when can you watch videos of how to
do something and and learn how to do it
as opposed to
uh being given a lot of task
demonstrations.
Sorry, do you have more to add there?
You're muted if you're
Yeah, I think um
um
Yeah, I think there are other ways also
to bring this knowledge like obviously
in context learning
is one way to enable continual learning.
Imagine like one way I think about is
that imagine we had an infinite context
that the model could perfectly have
access to every piece of it and could
learn from everything in it. We don't
have that, but if we had that, maybe
that was one solution to like
continual learning, right? Because we
could put everything positive and
negative in the context and the model
could just remember all of that at the
same time and reason over all of that at
the same time.
But, we don't have that. And we go
through right now even a million or a
few million, the models like kind of uh
keep ability to reason over its ICL or
in context uh kind of data diminishes.
Um and there are other ways like we
learned about cartridge in this tape in
this uh in the span of our lectures. So,
that's one other way that
to be our enabling this long context and
in context learning without changing the
weights of the model, without fine
fine-tuning it fine-tuning the model,
but instead bringing them into the
activations or in this case into the KB
caches of the model. So, um
all I'm saying here is that there are
other ways to think about like continual
learning uh without model
without model fine-tuning. One could be
by just increasing the effe- effective
context length uh massively. Um
and that could be another approach to
memory like long-term memory and uh and
continual learning.
>> As a as a sort of follow-up to that,
like
in in practice, like in implementation,
like do you think you know, what what
would be easier to do? Like, you know,
constantly updating the model's weights
or uh you know, updating a memory store,
right?
>> So, I I I think it depends on the
application, right? I mean, uh of course
you can argue that updating the memory
store
would would be easier. Um if it's a
knowledge base, if what you're I mean,
the simplest and naive version of that
is that if I could keep a database that
the LM could learn to look at, then I
should just go update the database,
right? But what you're really trying to
teach the LM is to the ability to reason
over new domains, and and oftentimes
having a side memory system doesn't
quite achieve that. So that's where
updating the weights does the job
better. And the example that I was
giving in robotics actually is very
very pertinent there as to like no
matter how much
memory systems you add, the robot which
has learned, I mean, the
cross-embodiment generalization that you
were looking at on the lecture on
Monday, for example, that doesn't happen
if you don't update the LM weights just
by by having memory systems, right? So
that's more of a skills transfer
problem.
>> Okay, makes sense. Yeah, thanks so much.
>> Okay, there's one more question, I think
from
What he's saying is that in the zero in
the absolute zero paper, the environment
seems like the data used for
post-training is in the paper for agents
to self-create environments.
So um
I mean, if you go back to the worlds
where there was narrow intelligence,
right?
There you could basically create
simulations for games. So
and those were used as environments for
toy tasks.
The
The reason environments matter in the
current generation are that they are
proxies for real-world tasks. So it's
not so much that there's a paper for
agents to self-create environments, it's
more along the lines of what is the set
of tasks that you're trying to
represent. Um
if there is an easy way to simulate
them, then
whether you use agents to create that or
software to create that, that's fairly
straightforward, but is it a reasonable
proxy of
how the model will interact with the
real world to get feedback.
And for gaming
it's
kind of a finite space to explore, so
it's easier to represent that in code
and have simulations.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Uh more questions from the class?
You were saying something?
>> I was saying
no questions.
>> Okay, we can't hear you, Jared. You have
to speak up.
>> I I think he said there are no further
questions.
>> Okay, awesome.
>> Uh okay, cool.
>> Okay, so let's start by let's end by
thanking the class. It's been a It's
been a real pleasure teaching you all
and creating the content for this class
so that you can learn about the latest
and greatest set of techniques in the
self-improving agents
area. It's a evolving area, so anything
that we teach now starts to be history
by the next time the class rolls around,
so and yet the basic techniques that
you're learning um are extremely
valuable over time because a lot of the
new stuff still builds on top of the
basic techniques.
So, really grateful to have worked with
you all and looking forward to what you
do in your projects and in your posters.
And let Azalia also thank the class.
>> Yes, thank you so much for
uh kind of
the way we created this class is that we
were also learning about a lot of things
as we were creating the slides and we
were preparing the course material
because a lot of these topics are just
like so fresh and so new and we were
excited about them and we wanted you to
also be aware of them. So,
thanks for like kind of accompanying us
in this journey journey and we're very
grateful to you and we hope that you
learned
uh
you learned some new skills, you got
inspired in some new direction
directions and we really hope that this
is just the beginning for you to do to
go ahead and do so so many more amazing
work in your research projects, in your
jobs, and in the future in general. So,
thank you so much.